# Nikhil Kabbin

#### Bangalore, India

+91-9986075548 | nikhil.kabbin@gmail.com

## **Professional Profile**

A Python and Web Technologies programmer with newly acquired skills, over 3 years of experience in Data Analysis and Visualization, with the ability to mine hidden gems located within large sets of structured, semi-structured and unstructured data. Able to leverage a heavy dose of applied statistics with visualization and a healthy sense of exploration.

## **Skills**

- Python, Pandas, R, VB Script
- NoSQL data stores (Mongo DB)
- Hadoop, MySQL, Map Reduce
- HTML5, Core JavaScript
- d3.js, underscore.js, leaflet.js
- Web & Print Content Development

- Data Scraping/Mining,
- Applied Statistic Models
- Microsoft Excel, Power BI
- Data Visualization
- Scaling, performance and scheduling and ETL techniques

## **Education**

## Master of Science, 9.37 GPA

Manipal University, Manipal

- June 2013
- Major: Embedded and Wireless Communications

## **Bachelor of Engineering, 6.36 GPA**

**VTU University, Belgaum** 

- June, 2011
- Major: Computer Science and Software Engineering

# **Professional Experience**

**GRAMENER**, Bangalore, IN – Data Analytics and Visualization Company

#### Data Specialist, May 2014 to Present

Work closely with various clients to identify and solve business challenges utilizing large structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data in a distributed processing environment.

- Analyze large datasets to provide strategic direction to the company.
- Perform quantitative analysis of product sales trends to recommend pricing decisions.
- Develop statistical models to forecast inventory and procurement cycles.
- Assist in developing internal tools for data analysis and visualizations.

#### **Selected Accomplishments:**

• Developed and integrated, Intellectual Property Analysis (Patents Text Mining and Analysis) for Aerospace Engineering Company.

Ref: https://gramener.com/ipanalysis/

- Developed Link Analysis Dashboard that enhanced fraud analysis team which reveals the key fraud connections.
- Developed Web-crawler for scrapping data from client specific web portals and dashboard to analyze Human resource management and replacement cost analysis.

## Associate Data Specialist, May 2013 to Apr 2014

Coded, tested, debugged, implemented and documented apps using Web Technologies and Python. Built report interfaces and data feeds. Gathered and collected information from various programs, analyzed time requirements and prepared documentation to change existing programs.

#### **Selected Accomplishments:**

- Designed and Developed Windows 8 Application for Banking products performances analysis and visualization integrating Heat-map over interactive Geographic Maps.
  - Ref: https://gramener.com/microsoft/banking.html
- Contribution to Internal Visualization Product
- Developed framework that controls the Windows 8 Application interface, to customize Dashboard and its controls.

# Visualization Developer (Intern), Aug 2012 to May 2013

A great Data Science learning curve. Anonymizing client's dashboards for show casing use case and learning data analysis and identifying key insights through visualizations with real world problems.

#### **Selected Accomplishments:**

- Generating and Automating visualizations through Microsoft PowerPoint.
- Karnataka Election Data Analysis and Visualization for Print Media. Responsible for design and development of interesting visualizations on the history of Karnataka elections, from 1952 to 2013.

See the published Analysis and Visualizations here: https://gramener.com/vijaykarnataka

## **Publications**

Title : Analysis of IP over IEEE 802.15.4 using 6LoWPAN and Implementation in WSNs.

**Conference**: Fourth National Conference for Information Science, MCIS Manipal.

## Volunteer

#### DataKind, Bangalore chapter

Volunteering to conduct meetups on Data Science and help Non-Profit Organization to solve data science problem. Also share data science knowledge through workshops and talks.

#### **Selected Accomplishments:**

• Developing a video recommendation engine for agriculturists through Machine learning methods and consideration of soil and weather data.

